# Nicholas **Nelson**

# PhD Student, Computer Science | Software Developer

https://oregonstate.edu/~nelsonni

**(b)** ORCID:0000-0002-6365-7152 **(3)** Nicholas.Nelson DBLP:Nelson 0002:Nicholas

1 +1 541 224 6912 @ nelsonni@oregonstate.edu

2500 NW Monroe Avenue, Corvallis, Oregon 97331, USA



PhD student in Computer Science focusing on software engineering (SE), human-computer interaction (HCI), user interfaces, and developer tools. I am exploring the effects of human problem-solving processes on the use of integrated development environments (IDEs). I also conduct research into software development processes such as merge conflicts, continuous integration (CI), and test-driven development (TDD). I have experience using TypeScript, Java, CSS, C/C++, SQL, Python, PHP, JSON, and R.

# **EDUCATION**

2015-Current Ph.D in Computer Science at Oregon State University (Advisor: Anita Sarma)

2015 B.S. in Computer Science at Oregon State University (Minor: Business & Entrepreneurship)

2008 A.S. in Computer Information Systems at Portland Community College

2008 A.S. in General Studies at Portland Community College

2003 H.S. Diploma at South Albany High School



# **EMPLOYMENT**

# September 2019 June 2019

# Research Intern - Program Synthesis, MICROSOFT CORPORATION, USA

> Human-computer interaction (HCI) research project with Titus Barik.

Typescript React Angular Visual Studio Code C#

# Present September 2015

# Graduate Research & Teaching Assistant, OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY, USA

- > Developed architecture and platform for a highly-configurable context-oriented IDE.
- > Conducted empirical research into cognitive processes of problem-solving and context management during software development.
- > Conducted research into developer perceptions of software merge conflict processes and tools.
- > Developed IntelliJ Idea plugin to analyze and refactor Android Java code written for API 6/7 security to use API 8 runtime permissions.
- > Assisted with research into developer perceptions of Continuous Integration (CI) practices and tools.
- > Reviewed submitted manuscripts for prominent software engineering conferences.

Typescript Javascript | jQuery | CSS | NodeJS | Atom | LaTeX | IntelliJ Idea | Git | Maven | Gradle | Groovy Android Studio | Android 8 API | TravisCI | Jenkins | JSON | R | RStudio | Haskell | Idris | Prolog

# September 2015 March 2014

#### Undergraduate Research Assistant, OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY, USA

- > Member of Change-Oriented Programming Environment (COPE) research group.
- > Assisted with research into predictive code analysis and visualization of Test-Driven Development (TDD) developer processes.

Java IntelliJ Idea | Git | Maven | LaTeX | Eclipse | R | RStudio | Ninja Framework | Ruby | Python | XML

# March 2014 September 2013

#### Undergraduate Teaching Assistant, OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY, USA

- > Instructed recitation labs for 30–40 freshman and sophomore computer science students enrolled in Computer Science Orientation (CS160), Introduction to Computer Science I (CS161), and Introduction to Computer Science II (CS162) courses.
- > Developed training and evaluation material for new teaching assistants.

Python Java C/C++ PyCharm IntelliJ Idea

# September 2013 June 2013

### Process Engineering Intern, HEWLETT PACKARD ENTERPRISE, USA

- > Member of PPS Inkjet High-Speed Production Solutions (IHPS) division.
- > Designed, proposed, and implemented warranty processing and validation code for HP Web Press consumable products.
- > Integrated file code with HP Web Press Dashboard web applications.

Python PHP Perl Bash

# December 2012 April 2010

# System Analyst I, SAMARITAN HEALTH SERVICES, USA

- > Member of Information Services (IS) division.
- > Provided technical support, evaluation, deployment, maintenance, project management, and sunset strategizing for 85 enterprise software applications.
- > Maintained primary application support for 30 enterprise applications, including 24/7 support during on-call rotations.

Oracle SQL MySQL PostgreSQL Microsoft Windows Server Bomgar Remote Access Schlage Lock Control Software ViewPAK Boiler System | Microsoft SharePoint | Microsoft Active Directory

# April 2010 July 2008

#### Help Desk Analyst, Samaritan Health Services, USA

- > Member of Information Services (IS) division.
- > Provided technical support for 7,000 healthcare employees.
- > Maintained a 99% yearly customer satisfaction rating.
- > Answered 13,000 phone calls and 7,000 support emails per year.

BMC Remedy Service Management | Polycom Teleconference | LogMeIn Remote Control

# July 2008 October 2007

#### UNIX Server Operations Intern, INTEL CORPORATION, USA

- > Developed interactive web applications for server systems rack polling and management.
- > Supported 6,000 production and test UNIX/Linux servers in active use by engineers and developers.
- > Maintained operational security for 700 highly secure hardened UNIX/Linux servers co-located in secure global facilities.

ColdFusion PHP Java Python Perl

# October 2007 May 2007

#### Engineering Computing Support Intern, INTEL CORPORATION, USA

- > Provided technical support for 19,000 Engineering and Product Development employees.
- > Supported 160+ enterprise software products across 14 different global sites.
- > Developed SQL queries and reports for weekly and monthly support statistics.

BMC Remedy Service Management | TrueWindow Remote Access Control | Microsoft Active Directory



# PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- \* co-first author.
- [8] Souti Chattopadhyay, Nicholas Nelson, Yenifer Ramirez Gonzalez, Annel Amelia Leon, Rahul Pandita, and Anita Sarma. Latent Patterns in Activities: A Field Study of How Developers Manage Context. Proceedings of the ACM/IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE'19), May 2019. Acceptance ratio: 20.6% (109/529).
- [7] Nicholas Nelson, Caius Brindescu, Shane McKee, Anita Sarma, and Danny Dig. The Life-Cycle of Merge Conflicts: Processes, Barriers, and Strategies. Empirical Software Engineering Journal (EMSE), February 2019.
- [6] Souti Chattopadhyay, Nicholas Nelson, Thien Nam, McKenzie Calvert, and Anita Sarma. Context in Programming: An Investigation of How Programmers Create Context. Proceedings of the IEEE ICSE Workshop on Cooperative and Human Aspects of Software Engineering (CHASE'18), May 2018.
- [5] Shane McKee\*, Nicholas Nelson\*, Anita Sarma, and Danny Dig. Software Practitioner Perspectives on Merge Conflicts and Resolutions. Proceedings of IEEE International Conference on Software Maintenance and Evolution (ICSME'17), Sep 2017. Acceptance ratio: 27.8% (42/151). TIEEE TCSE Distinguished Paper Award.
- [4] Michael Hilton, Nicholas Nelson, Timothy Tunnell, Darko Marinov, and Danny Dig. Trade-offs in Continuous Integration: Assurance, Security, and Flexibility. Proceedings of ACM SIGSOFT Symposium on the Foundations of Software Engineering (FSE'17), Sep 2017. Acceptance ratio: 24.4% (72/295). **PACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award**.
- [3] Nicholas Nelson, Anita Sarma, and André van der Hoek. Towards an IDE to Support Programming as Problem-Solving. Proceedings of the Psychology of Programming Interest Group Workshop (PPIG'17), Jul 2017. Acceptance ratio: 84.0% (21/25).
- [2] Nicholas Nelson. Problem-Solving Applications in Developer Environments. pages 179–180. Proceedings of the Psychology of Programming Interest Group Workshop (PPIG'17), Jul 2017. Acceptance ratio: 90.0% (9/10).
- [1] Michael Hilton, Nicholas Nelson, Hugh McDonald, Sean McDonald, Ron Metoyer, and Danny Dig. TDDViz: Using Software Changes to Understand Conformance to Test Driven Development. pages 53-65. Proceedings of the International Conference on Agile Processes, in Software Engineering, and Extreme Programming (XP'16), May 2016. Acceptance ratio: 33.3% (14/42).



Englich	••••
•	
Spanish	
German	
Mandarin	• 0 0 0 0
Japanese	• 0 0 0 0



- > ACM SIGSOFT CAPS Travel Support Award at ICSE'19
- > IEEE TCSE Distinguished Paper Award at ICSME'17
- > ACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award at FSE'17
- > Honor Roll at OSU for Winter'15, Fall'14, Winter'14, Spring'14
- > President's List at PCC for Spring'08
- > Dean's List at PCC for Winter'08, Fall'07, Winter'07



2019 Reviewer, 27TH ACM JOINT EUROPEAN SOFTWARE ENGINEERING CONFERENCE AND SYMPOSIUM ON THE FOUNDATIONS OF SOFTWARE ENGINEERING (ESEC/FSE)

Tallinn, Estonia

Reviewer, 34TH IEEE/ACM International Conference on Automated Software Engineering (ASE) San Diego, California, USA

2018 Reviewer, 33RD IEEE/ACM INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON AUTOMATED SOFTWARE ENGINEERING (ASE)
Montpellier, France

2016–2018 | Steward, Coalition of Graduate Employees Local 6069 (AFT, AFL-CIO), USA

> Graduate employee representative for Electrical Engineering and Computer Science (EECS).

2017 Video Game Workshop Lead, CHICKTECH CORVALLIS, USA

> Developed instructional material for 2017 ChickTech Corvallis Annual Summer Kickoff Event for 200-300 high school girls interested in science and technology.

Reviewer, 32ND IEEE/ACM International Conference on Automated Software Engineering (ASE) Urbana-Champaign, Illinois, USA

Reviewer, 30TH ACM SYMPOSIUM ON USER INTERFACE SOFTWARE AND TECHNOLOGY (UIST) Quebec City, Canada

Reviewer, 14TH INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON MINING SOFTWARE REPOSITORIES (MSR) Buenos Aires, Argentina

Reviewer, 30TH IEEE/ACM International Conference on Automated Software Engineering (ASE) Lincoln, Nebraska, USA



#### Dr. Anita Sarma

Associate Professor, Computer Science
OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY

2015

@ anita.sarma@oregonstate.edu

https://web.engr.oregonstate.edu/~sarmaa

+1 (541) 737-5985

# Dr. Michael Hilton

Assistant Teaching Professor, Institute for Software Research CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY

@ mhilton@cmu.edu

http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~mhilton

**L** +1 (619) 933-3451

#### Dr. André van der Hoek

Professor & Department Chair, Informatics University of California, Irvine

@ andre@ics.uci.edu

http://www.ics.uci.edu/~andre

+1 (949) 824-6326

# Dr. Danny Dig

Associate Professor, Computer Science
OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY

@ digd@eecs.oregonstate.edu

https://web.engr.oregonstate.edu/~digd

+1 (619) 933-3451